你们有没有想过
There is much speculation by some
阿波罗任务中的计算机是怎么
as to how the flight computer aboard the Apollo missions
把人类送上月球的
managed to get men to the moon
在那时计算机运算能力都不如现在的
when it had just a tiny fraction of the computing power of something like
一个智能手机
a modern smartphone
但首先这里有个误区
But this is quite misleading
就是说阿波罗上不是只有一个计算机
as there was not one solitary computer controlling the Apollo craft
而是四个，没有花花绿绿的触摸屏
there were 4 computers and no fancy touch screens
没有图形界面，为了节省资源，如今各种计算机有的功能它都没有
GUI’s or other things in a typical computer of today to waste resources on
四台计算机中第一台是运载火箭数字计算机，LVDC
The first of the 4 computers was the Saturn Launch Vehicle Digital Computer or LVDC
它控制火箭从发射架起飞到近地轨道
this got the rocket from the launch pad to earth orbit
之后就是阿波罗导航计算机，AGC了
Then there was the Apollo Guidance Computer or AGC
这是绝大多数人比较关注的
this is the one the most people think of
实际上，这当中有两台
There were in fact, two of them
一台在指令舱中，控制阿波罗号从地球飞到月球再飞回来
one in the Command Module to get from the earth orbit to the moon and back again
第二台在登月舱里，控制月球着陆
The second was in the lunar lander that would control the landing
再次起飞和与指令舱对接
and then the ascent back to the command module and docking
最后一台计算机在阿波罗系列任务中从来没用过
The fourth computer was one which was never used on any missions
因为它在月球下降、着陆过程中控制紧急终止并再次起飞
because it would control an emergency abort and ascent
should something happen during the descent to the moons surface
如果在这期间着陆计算机失效或者燃油告急
like the landing computer failing or they ran out of fuel
AGC并不像当年其他计算机那样特别笨重
The Apollo Guidance Computer wasn’t as dumb as many make it out to be
在阿波罗任务研发过程中
As time when by in Apollo’s development
大量有难度的任务源源不断
the tasks that it was meant to do increased in both number and sophistication
由于资源有限，随之带来的问题也越来越多
This in turn created ever more issues with the limited resources available
其中最大的问题就是存储空间不够
One of the biggest problems was the limited amount of memory
鉴于当时技术限制
due to the technological limitations of the time
程序员必须充分利用每一字节的空间
this meant that the programmers had to make use of every single byte available
AGC还有一个独一无二的操作系统
The AGC also had a unique operating system
就像UNIX、Linux、Windows和iOS一样
Systems like UNIX, Linux, Windows and Apple iOS
用来控制各种程序分配的时间
are in control and share time out to the programs
在AGC里，程序运行的时间是由其重要程度来决定的
In the AGC, the programs controlled how much time they got depending on how important they were
比如在紧急情况下
So in the case of an emergency
最高优先级的程序就会得到最多的运行时间
the highest priority programs would get most amount of the time
其他无关操作就会被搁置来释放资源
and non-essential operations were dropped to free up resources
这个理念成为了之后许多载人任务系统中的关键
which became the basis of mission critical system for all manned mission afterwards
AGC的性能和
The computer had a performance somewhere around that of
第一代PC差不多
the first generation of personal computers
像Apple II, commodore 64, ZX Spectrum
like the Apple II, commodore 64, ZX Spectrum
但它们都是70年代末才出现的
which would arrive 10 years later in the late 70’s
AGC有2k的RAM、36K的ROM
It had 2k of RAM and 36k of fixed storage rope core memory or ROM
全部纯手工打造，要花费几个月时间
and this was woven by hand and took months to assemble
所以任何Bugs真的是被“塞”进去的(233
so any software bugs were literally woven into the system
用AGC和现在iPhone 6做对比
A comparison between the Apollo Guidance Computer and say an iPhone 6
有点不严谨，因为AGC不属于通用计算机
is tricky because the AGC was not a general purpose computer
它是用来做非常特殊的任务的，拥有独一无二的操作系统
It was built for a very specific task, had a unique operating system
而且中间还差48年的科技进步
That and also the 48-year gap in the technologies used
所以我们只能非常粗略的估计它们之间性能差异
mean we can only really get very rough estimates on the differency performance
苹果iPhone 6搭载ARM A8处理器
The Apple iPhone 6 has the ARM A8 processor
有16亿晶体管，AGC有12300个
which has about 1.6 billion transistors in it, the AGC had just 12,300
iPhone 6有1G的RAM，是AGC的488000倍
This iPhone 6 has 1Gb of RAM, about 488,000 times the AGC
128G的ROM，大概是AGC的350万倍
and this one, 128Gb of non-volatile storage or about 3.5 million times the AGC
至于性能，iPhone 6大概是AGC的
As for performance, the iPhone 6 is maybe somewhere
400万到3000万倍
between 4 and 30 Million times faster than the AGC
这要看是做什么类型的计算
depending upon what type of calculations are being done
要是算上iPhone的GPU，那就更多了
and if you include the iPhone’s GPU it would be even more
所以如果你在阿波罗飞船上要登月了
So, if you had to fly back to the moon in an Apollo craft and given the choice
你会把你性命托付给几个iPhone还是AGC？
would you trust your life to a couple of iPhones in place of the AGC’s?
别忘了你们用来上B站给UP投币的智能手机运算能力可是比
because you would actually have more computing power in just one of these
当年阿波罗任务中全NASA拥有的计算机总和都高到不知道哪里去
than the whole of NASA had during all the Apollo missions
但万一你的iPhone死机，那你就凉了
However, if your iPhone crashed you would be in big trouble
因为AGC虽然古老，但它是专门设计可以从死机、过载等情况恢复过来
whereas the ancient AGC was designed to recover from crashes or overloads
自动继续运行，说白了，它不怕死机
and continue by itself, in essence, it was designed to be crash proof
在任务的一些关键时刻这是非常重要的
something that is needed in mission critical situations
对比两种计算机啊，当然要看性能，但也要考虑历史的进程！
The problem we have here is the context in which we see the Apollo computer today
今天我们身边有那么多计算机，性能那么强
We are now surrounded by computers, hugely more powerful
我们却以为那是理所当然的
and we don’t give them a second thought
但在当时那个年代，对于一个不是计算机工程师
It’s very difficult for most people who are not computer engineers
或者不是汇编语言程序员来说，用那么少的资源做这件事
or assembler language programmers to imagine how you could do anything
难度超乎想象
with such limited resources
别忘了这东西是1962年设计出来的
What we forget is that at the time of the design in 1962
可以说是世界上第一台嵌入式计算机
this was to be the first embedded computer
简直是小型计算机的一大步
It was huge leap forward in miniaturised computing
计算机突然从房子那么大变成公文包那么大
From something the size of a large room to the size of a briefcase
这也是软件编程技术的大跃进
It would also be giant leap forward for software programming
软件第一次用来实时处理问题
and the first time that software would be used for real-time problem solving
这是整个任务的关键，没有它不一定会死多少人
that would be key to the entire mission, if it failed then people could die
但它的研发难度简直了都
But its development was far from easy
据说如果最开始研发人员预测到了1961年他们将要面对的难题
It’s said that if the designers had known then in 1961 what they learned later
或者对合同让他们造什么有个清楚的了解
or had a complete specification when given the contract to make it
他们肯定会认为这件事
They would have most likely concluded
在当时，以60年代的科技水平是完全不可能的
that it was just not have been possible with early 1960s technology
阿波罗导航系统
The contract of the design development construction
和软件的设计研发合同
of the Apollo guidance navigation systems and software
在1961年8月签给了麻省理工学院
was given to the MIT in August 1961
而没有给NASA的老客户IBM
instead of NASA's normal computer contractors IBM
合同里说的并不详细
But there was no specifications given in the contract
因为在阿波罗研发早期，就连在NASA
because no one in NASA really knew
也没人能说清这“导航计算机”到底要干嘛
what the requirement of an Apollo computer would be at that early stage
而在60年代，整整十年里，这项工程的
As the project developed throughout the 1960s, it became apparent
巨大难度才慢慢浮出水面，远远超乎最开始人们的想象
that the task was going to be much more difficult than they first considered
60年代中后期
By the mid to late 60s
计算机的研发问题已经关乎到
the problems in the computers' development were in danger of sinking
整个阿波罗计划的生死存亡了
be entire of Apollo program if they couldn't get the AGC to work
1966年，在命运多舛的阿波罗1号测试中
By the time of testing in 1966 for the ill-fated Apollo 1
人们发现AGC软件里的Bug
it became apparent that bugs in the software meant that the AGC
会导致导航路径不可靠
couldnot be relied upon to do the navigational course calculations
说白了它算不准
as it was just not accurate enough
搞不好飞船返回的时候就进错轨道了
something that could put the craft into the wrong orbit when it returned to earth
最开始决定在地面用IBM的大型计算机做轨道计算
It was decided that IBM mainframe computers on the ground would do the course
然后把数据发送到指令舱的AGC上去执行
calculations and send them to the AGC in the command module to be implemented
这种方法可以把问题都
This way round, known limitations could be worked around
在地面上用更强大的计算机解决再传回AGC
with much more powerful ground based computers and the results then sent to the AGCs
但指令舱必须有自行计算的能力
However, the command module had to be capable of working independently
防止与地面的通讯失效，比如飞到月球背面
if the ground link was broken like when it was flying behind the moon
或者有其他信号干扰
or if someone tried to jam the signal
所以利用惯性导航
So using a combination of the inertial guidance system
与观察星位结合的方法定位
and built in Sextant to check the star positions
计算机仍然能在无需地面链接的情况下进行导航
they could still navigate without a ground-linked data
至于登月舱，信号发到地球再传回月球
As for the lander, the round trip delay of 1.5 seconds
各会有一秒半的延迟
for the signals to get to the moon and back to earth
这个延迟对于下降段着陆控制来说实在是太大了
would have been too long for ground control to remotely land the descent stage
因为各种反馈必须实时处理
because the feedback needed to be in real time
最后，下降级AGC
To this end, the descent stage AGC
要和着陆雷达、宇航员共同合作才能在月球着陆
would work with the landing radar and the astronauts to land on the moon
这让阿波罗11号任务在最后阶段差点取消
This led to the Apollo 11 landing almost being aborted
当时着陆雷达里有个BUG
when a design bug in the landing radar
登月舱下降的时候为了防止紧急终止，着陆雷达被设成待命状态
which had been left on standby during the descent in case of an emergency abort
制造了一堆信号导致AGC计算机过载，在着陆前触发了
created a flood of signals that overloaded the AGC and setting off computer error
计算机代码错误警告
code alarms just before the landing
对于AGC的设计，不像我们心中
Due to the AGC’s design, instead of crashing or locking up
iPhone或者普通的电脑会崩溃或者锁定
like we maybe expect our iPhone or normal computer to do
它在重启前会把最重要的任务以外的都舍弃
it dropped all but the most important tasks before then restarting itself
这不是它的缺陷，这叫重置保护
This was not a fault, it was called RESET Protection
AGC的设计会让它保存所有目前运算的数据
The AGC was designed so that all of the current data it was working on was stored
使它能在任何时候关闭、再打开或者重置
This meant that it could be turned off and on again or reset at any time
之后它会从之前的地方继续运算
and it would just continue to work from where it left off
有点像PC的睡眠模式再开机
a bit like when your PC goes into sleep mode and then come back again
但比这快多了
but much, much quicker
这些特性让阿波罗11号任务最后没有终止，而是让阿姆斯特朗接手
These features saved the mission from aborting and allowed Armstrong to control
控制了登月舱的航向
the orientation of the lander
同时AGC控制登月舱的下降，最后成功着陆
whilst the AGC controlled the descent to a successful landing.
说白了在阿波罗计划里，人类用性能堪比如今烤面包机芯片的计算机
Its things like this that made what is now about as powerful as the microcontroller
把人安全的送上月球并返回，整整六次
in a toaster get men to the moon and safely back again, 6 times
它不但为之后的太空探索提供了范例
It also created a paradigm shift not only in space exploration
也促进了之后计算机的发展
but also computing for the future
最后感谢观看，字幕翻译给虫，YouTuber叫Curious Droid
别忘了点赞、投币、关注、分享、收藏~
And as always, thanks for watching, and please subscribe, rate, and share